<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Toa on Android Essence</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/toa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Toa on Android Essence</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/toa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Five Essential Developer Experience Concepts For Android</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2021-09-10-essential-dev-experience-concepts-android/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2021-09-10-essential-dev-experience-concepts-android/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the most recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ePpbpLyYI1w&#34;&gt;live stream&lt;/a&gt; for Tasks Of Affirmation, we looked at creating a good developer experience. It&amp;rsquo;s important to consider developers at the start of any new project, so we can ensure that over the lifetime of a project anyone who contributes can understand how to contribute, match any guidelines that a team has, and get up and running quickly. We also want to ensure that our codebase maintains a certain quality of formatting and a lack of code smells - and putting these checks in place before you even start prevents them from ever being introduced at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at five developer experience concepts I consider essential to every project.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tasks Of Affirmation: A New Twitch Live Stream Series</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2021-09-02-toa-twitch-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2021-09-02-toa-twitch-series/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the late summer of 2020, I began live streaming on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitch.com/adammc331&#34;&gt;my Twitch channel&lt;/a&gt;. We started off by building an &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/adammc331/AndroidStudyGuide&#34;&gt;Android Study Guide&lt;/a&gt; application. The purpose of the application was to build something people would be interested in using, while also taking the opportunity to build an application out in the open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a number of reasons, discussed in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8Umvlpx-Wvg&#34;&gt;the latest video&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to sunset that project and begin a new live stream series: Tasks Of Affirmation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
